(Arabic) I seek refuge in Allah from cursed Satan. In the Name of Allah, the most Gracious, the most Merciful.
أعوذ بالله من الشيطان الرجيم، بسم الله الرحمان الرحيم
(English) I was born in a middle class family.
ولدت في عائلة من الطبقة المتوسطة.
My father was five years old when he lost his father,
كان والدي في الخامسة من عمره عندما توفّي والده،
but by the time I was born,
ولكن بحلول الوقت الذي وُلدت فيه،
he was already a businessman.
كان قد أصبح رجل أعمالٍ.
But it didn't make a difference to him
لكن هذا لم يشكل فرقاً بالنسبة له
if his children were going to be a boy or a girl:
إذا كان أطفاله ذكوراً أو إناثاً
they were going to go to school.
سيتسنى لهم الإلتحاق بالمدرسة.
So I guess I was the lucky one.
لذا أعتقد أنني كنت محظوظة.
My mother had 16 pregnancies.
حملت أمي 16 مرةً.
From 16 pregnancies, five of us are alive.
من بين 16 حالة حمل، نجى خمسة منا فقط.
You can imagine as a child what I went through.
يمكنكم أن تتخيل المعاناة التي مررت بها كطفلة.
Day to day, I watched women
يوما بعد يوم، شاهدت النساء
being carried to a graveyard,
وهن ينقلن إلى المقبرة،
or watched children going to a graveyard.
أو رأيت الأطفال يتم دفنهم في المقبرة.
At that time, when I finished my high school,
في ذلك الوقت، وعندما أكملت مرحلة الثانوية،
I really wanted to be a doctor.
أردت بشدة أن أصبح طبيبةً.
I wanted to be a doctor to help women and children.
أردت أن أصبح طبيبة لأساعد النساء والأطفال.
So I completed my education,
لذا, أكملت دراستي،
but I wanted to go to university.
ولكن أردت الإلتحاق بالجامعة.
Unfortunately, in my country, there wasn't a dormitory for girls,
ولسوء الحظ، لم يكن هناك مهجع للطالبات في بلدي
so I was accepted in medical school, but I could not go there.
فلقد تم قبولي في كلية الطب، ولكن لم أتمكن من الذهاب إلى هناك.
So as a result, my father sent me to America.
وكنتيجة لذلك،قام أبي بإرسالي إلى أمريكا.
I came to America.
وصلت إلى أمريكا.
I completed my education.
أكملت دراستي.
While I was completing my education,
بينما كنت في مرحلة إتمام دراستي،
my country was invaded by Russia.
قامت روسيا بغزو بلدي.
And do you know that at the time I was completing my education,
وهل تعرفون أنه في الوقت الذي كنت أكمل فيه دراستي،
I didn't know what was going on with my family or with my country.
لم أكن على علم بما كان يحدث مع عائلتي أو بلدي.
There were months, years, I didn't know about it.
لم أكن على علمٍ بذلك لأشهرٍ وسنواتٍ.
My family was in a refugee camp.
كانت عائلتي موجودةً في مخيم للاجئين.
So as soon as I completed my education,
ولذلك ما إن أنهيت دراستي،
I brought my family to America.
قمت بإحضار عائلتي إلى أمريكا.
I wanted them to be safe.
أردتهم أن يكونوا آمنين بعيدا عن الخطر.
But where was my heart?
ولكن أين كان قلبي؟
My heart was in Afghanistan.
كان قلبي في أفغانستان.
Day after day, when I listened to the news,
يوم بعد يوم، عندما استمع إلى الأخبار،
when I followed what was going on with my country,
عندما اتابع ما كان يحدث مع بلدي،
my heart was breaking up.
كان قلبي يتحطم.
I really wanted to go back to my country,
أردت حقا العودة إلى بلدي،
but at the same time I knew I could not go there,
ولكن في نفس الوقت كنت أعرف أنه لا يمكنني الذهاب إلى هناك،
because there was no place for me.
لأنه لا يوجد مكان لي.
I had a good job.
كنت أشغل وظيفة جيدة.
I was a professor at a university.
كنت أستاذة جامعيّةً.
I earned good money.
كسبت الكثير من المال.
I had a good life.
كانت حياتي جيدةً.
My family was here.
كانت عائلتي هنا.
I could live with them.
يمكنني العيش معهم.
But I wasn't happy.
ولكنني لم أكن أشعر بالسعادة.
I wanted to go back home.
أردت العودة إلى أرض الوطن.
So I went to the refugee camp.
لذلك ذهبت إلى مخيم اللاجئين.
And when I went to the refugee camp in Pakistan,
عندما وصلت إلى مخيم اللاجئين في باكستان،
there were 7.5 million refugees.
كان يضم 7.5 مليون لاجئ.
7.5 million refugees.
7.5 مليون لاجئٍ.
About 90 percent of them were women and children.
بلغت نسبة النساء والأطفال فيه 90 بالمئة تقريباً.
Most of the men have been killed or they were in war.
معظم الرجال كانوا قد قُتلوا , أو مازالوا يحاربون
And you know, in the refugee camp,
وكما تعرفون، عندما كنت في مخيم للاجئين،
when I went day-to-day to do a survey,
ذهبت يوما بعد يوم للقيام بمسحٍ،
I found things you never could imagine.
ووجدت أموراً لا يمكنكم حتى تصورها.
I saw a widow with five to eight children
رأيت أرملة بصحبة خمسة أو ثمانية أطفال
sitting there and weeping
جالسة هناك تبكي
and not knowing what to do.
ولا تعرف ما الذي يجب أن تفعله.
I saw a young woman have no way to go anywhere,
رأيت امرأة شابة ليس لديها طريقة أو وسيلة لتذهب إلى أي مكان،
no education, no entertainment, no place to even live.
بلا تعليم ولا تسلية ولا حتى مكان تعيش فيه.
I saw young men that had lost their father and their home,
رأيت شبابا فقدوا والدهم ومنزلهم،
and they are supporting the family as a 10-to-12-year old boy --
ويقومون بدعم الأسرة باعتبارهم في 10- 12 من العمر--
being the head of the household,
كونهم الذكور في الأسرة والمسؤولين عنها،
trying to protect their sister and their mother and their children.
يحاولون حماية شقيقاتهم وأمهاتهم وأطفالهم.
So it was a very devastating situation.
كان الوضع مدمرا للغاية.
My heart was beating for my people,
كان قلبي ينبض لشعبي،
and I didn't know what to do.
ولا أعرف ما الذي يجب أن أفعله.
At that moment, we talk about momentum.
في تلك اللحظة, وبالحديث عن القوة الدافعة والعزيمة.
At that moment, I felt, what can I do for these people?
في تلك اللحظة تبادر إلى ذهني، ما الذي يمكنني فعله لهؤلاء الأشخاص؟
How could I help these people?
كيف يمكنني أن أساعدهم؟
I am one individual. What can I do for them?
أنا بمفردي. ما الذي يمكنني أن أفعله لهم؟
But at that moment, I knew
ولكن في تلك اللحظة، أدركت
that education changed my life.
أن التعليم غيّر حياتي.
It transformed me. It gave me status.
قام بتحويلي. أعطاني منزلة.
It gave me confidence. It gave me a career.
منحني الثقة. قدم لي مهنة.
It helped me to support my family,
ساعدني على دعم أسرتي،
to bring my family to another country,
وجلب عائلتي إلى بلدٍ آخر،
to be safe.
ليكونوا في أمان.
And I knew that at that moment
وأدركت في تلك اللحظة
that what I should give to my people is education and health,
أن الذي يجب أن أقدمه لشعبي هو التعليم والصحة،
and that's what I went after.
وهذا ما ذهبت للقيام به.
But do you think it was easy?
ولكن هل تعتقدون أن الأمر كان سهلا؟
No, because at that time, education was banned for girls, completely.
لا، لأنه في ذلك الوقت، كان التعليم محظورا على الفتيات، بشكل تامٍّ.
And also, by Russia invading Afghanistan,
وأيضا، باجتياح روسيا لأفغانستان،
people were not trusting anyone.
كان الناس لا يثقون بأي أحدٍ.
It was very hard to come and say, "I want to do this."
كان صعبا أن تذهب إلى هناك وتخبرهم، "أريد القيام بهذا الأمر."
Who am I?
من أنا لأقوم بذلك؟
Somebody who comes from the United States.
شخص قدم من الولايات المتحدة الأمريكية.
Somebody who got educated here.
شخص حصل على تعليمه هناك.
Did they trust me? Of course not.
هل وثقوا بي؟ بالطبع لا.
So I really needed to build the trust in this community.
لذلك احتجت كسب ثقة المجتمع.
How am I going to do that?
كيف سأقوم بذلك؟
I went and surveyed and looked and looked.
ذهبت إلى هناك وقمت بدراسة وبحثت وبحثت.
I asked.
سألت في الأرجاء.
Finally, I found one man.
وجدت في نهاية المطاف رجلا.
He was 80 years old.
كان في 80 من عمره.
He was a mullah.
كان إمامَ مسجدٍ.
I went to his tent in the camp,
اتجهت صوب خيمته في المخيم،
and I asked him,
وأخبرته،
"I want to make you a teacher."
"أريد أن أجعلك معلما."
And he looked at me,
فنظر إليّ،
and he said, "Crazy woman,
وقال "إمرأةٌ مجنونة،
crazy woman, how do you think I can be a teacher?"
أيتها المجنونة، كيف تظنين أنه يمكنني أن أصبح معلما؟"
And I told him, "I will make you a teacher."
فكررت ما قلته له، "سأجعلك معلما."
Finally, he accepted my offer,
وفي نهاية المطاف، وافق على عرضي،
and once I started a class in his compound,
ما إن بدأت التدريس في مقره،
the word spread all over.
انتشر الخبر في كل مكانٍ.
In a matter of one year,
وفي غضون سنةٍ واحدةٍ،
we had 25 schools set up,
أصبح لدينا 25 مدرسةً،
15,000 children going to school,
و 15,000 طفل يرتاد المدرسة،
and it was amazing.
كان الأمر مدهشا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
But of course, we're doing all our work, we were giving teacher training.
وبالطبع, قمنا بكل أعمالنا، قدمنا تدريبا للمعلمين.
We were training women's rights, human rights, democracy, rule of law.
قدمنا تدريب في مجال حقوق المرأة، وحقوق الإنسان والديمقراطية وسيادة القانون.
We were giving all kinds of training.
كنا نوفر جميع أنواع التدريب.
And one day, I tell you,
وذات يومٍ، أخبركم،
one day I was in the office in Peshawar, Pakistan.
ذات يومٍ كنت في المكتب في بيشاور، باكستان.
All of a sudden, I saw my staff running to rooms and locking the doors
فجأة، رأيت الموظفين يركضون باتجاه الغرف ويغلقون الأبواب
and telling me, "Run away, hide!"
ويقولون لي، "اهربي، اختبئي!"
And you know, as a leader, what do you do?
وكما تعرفون، كقائد، ما الذي يمكنكم فعله؟
You're scared. You know it's dangerous.
تشعر بالخوف، تعرف أن الأمر خطيرٌ.
You know your life is on the line.
تعرف أن حياتك على حافة الخطر.
But as a leader, you have to hold it together.
ولكن كقائدٍ، يتوجب عليك التحكم بالأمور.
You have to hold it together and show strength.
يتوجب عليك الامساك بزمام الأمور والتظاهر بالقوة.
So I said, "What's going on?"
فقلت : " ما الذي يحدث؟"
And these people were pouring into my office.
وكان هؤلاء الأشخاص يتجهون صوب مكتبي.
So I invited them to the office.
فدعوتهم إلى دخول مكتبي.
They came, and there were nine of them -- nine Taliban.
دخلوا وقد كانوا تسعة أشخاص -- تسعة أشخاص من طالبان.
They were the ugliest looking men you can ever see.
كانوا أبشع رجال يمكنكم رؤيتهم في حياتكم.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Very mean-looking people,
يبدون خبثاءٌ جداً،
black clothes, black turban,
ملابس سوداء، عمائم سوداء،
and they pour into my office.
دخلوا مكتبي.
And I invited them to have a seat and have tea.
ودعوتهم للجلوس وشرب الشاي.
They said no. They are not going to drink tea.
فرفضوا شرب الشاي.
And of course, with the tone of voice they were using,
وبطبيعة الحال، مع حدة الصوت التي كانوا يتحدثون بها،
it was very scary,
كان الأمر مخيفا جدا،
but I was really shaking up.
كنت حقاً أرتعدُ من الخوف،
But also I was strong, holding myself up.
ولكنني كنت أيضاً قويةً في تمالك نفسي.
And, of course, by that time, you know how I dress --
وبطبيعة الحال، في ذلك الوقت، تعرفون كيف كان لباسي
I dress from head to toe in a black hijab.
ألبس حجاب أسود من الرأس إلى أخمص القدمين.
The only thing you could see, my eyes.
والشيء الوحيد الذي يمكنكم رؤيته، هو عينيّ
They asked me, "What are you doing?
سألونني، "ما الذي تقومين به؟
Don't you know that school is banned for girls?
ألا تعلمين أن المدارس محظورة على الفتيات؟
What are you doing here?"
ما الذي تفعلينه هنا؟"
And you know, I just looked at them,
وتعلمون، كنت أنظر إليهم فقط،
and I said, "What school? Where is the school?"
ثم أجبت: "عن أي مدرسة تتحدثون؟ أين هذه المدرسة؟"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
And they look at my face, and they said, "You are teaching girls here."
نظروا إليّ قائلين، " إنك تقومين بتعليم الفتيات هنا"
I said, "This is a house of somebody.
فأجبتهم "هذا منزل أحدهم.
We have some students coming,
يأتي بعض الطلاب إلى هنا،
and they are all learning Koran, Holy Book.
وكلهم يتعلمون القرآن، الكتاب المقدس للمسلمين.
And you know, Koran says that if you learn the Holy Book, the woman,
وكما تعلمون، يخبرنا القرآن بأنه إذا علّمنا النساء تعاليم القرآن
they can be a good wife,
فيمكنهن أن يصبحن زوجاتٍ صالحات،
and they can obey their husband."
وأن يطعن أزواجهنَّ."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And I tell you one thing:
سأخبركم أمرا واحدا:
that's the way you work with those people, and you know --
هذه هي الطريقة المثلى التي تصلح مع مع هؤلاء الناس كما تعلمون
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So by that time, they started speaking Pashto.
إذاً بعد قولي ذلك , بدأوا بالتحدث بلغة الباشتو.
They talked to each other,
تحدثوا مع بعضهم البعض،
and they said, "Let's go, leave her alone, she's OK."
ثم قالوا، "دعونا نذهب، فلنتركها وشأنها، فهي لا تشكل خطرا."
And you know, this time, I offered them tea again,
وهذه المرة, عرضت عليهم الشاي للمرة الثانية
and they took a sip and they left.
أخذوا منه رشفة وضحكوا.
By that time, my staff poured into my office.
بحلول ذلك الوقت، بدأ الموظفون بااتدفق إلى مكتبي.
They were scared to death.
كانوا يشعرون بالخوف الشديد إلى حد الموت.
They didn't know why they didn't kill me.
يجهلون لماذا لم يقوم هؤلاء الرجال بقتلي.
They didn't know why they didn't take me away.
ولا يعرفون لماذا لم يأخذونني بعيدا معهم.
But everybody was happy to see me.
ولكنه جميعاً كانوا سعداء لرؤيتي.
Very happy, and I was happy to be alive, of course.
سعداء للغاية، وأنا أيضا سعيدة لأنني على قيد الحياة، بالطبع.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Of course, I was happy to be alive.
بالطبع، كنت أشعر بالسعادة لأنني لازلت حيّة.
But also, as we continuously gave training during the fall of the Taliban --
مع مواصلتنا تقديم التدريبات خلال فترة سقوط طالبان--
of course during the Taliban there is another story.
بالطبع أصبح لدي قصة أخرى حدثت أثناء حركة طالبان.
We went underground and we provided education for 80 schoolgirls,
فقد نزلنا تحت الأرض ووفرنا التعليم لحوالي 80 تلميذةً،
3,000 students underground, and continuously we trained.
فكان لدينا 3,000 تلميذ تحت الأرض، وواصلنا تقديم التدريب.
With the fall of the Taliban, we went into the country,
وبعد سقوط طالبان، تمكنا من دخول بلادنا،
and we opened school after school.
وفتحنا المدارس الواحدة تلو الأخرى.
We opened women's learning center.
قمنا بفتح مركز تعليم للنساء.
We continuously opened clinics.
فتحنا العيادات بشكل مستمرٍّ.
We worked with mothers and children.
عملنا مع الأمهات والأطفال.
We had reproductive health training.
قمنا بالتدريب في مجال الصحة الإنجابية.
We had all kinds of training that you can imagine.
كان لدينا جميع أنواع التدريب التي يمكنكم تخيلها.
I was very happy. I was delighted with the outcome of my work.
كنت سعيدة جدا ومبتهجة بنتائج عملي.
And one day, with four trainers and one bodyguard,
وذات يومٍ، بصحبة أربعة مدربين وحارسٍ شخصيٍّ واحد،
I was going up north of Kabul,
كنت متوجهة إلى الشمال من كابول،
and all of a sudden, again,
وفجأة، ومرة أخرى،
I was stopped in the middle of the road
تم إيقافي في منتصف الطريق
by 19 young men.
من قِبلِ 19 شابا.
Rifles on their shoulders, they blocked the road.
سدوا الطريق، والبنادق على أكتافهم،
And I told my driver, "What's going on?"
فسألت السائق، "ما الذي يحدث؟"
And the driver said, "I don't know."
فأجابني، "لا أدري."
He asked them. They said, "We have nothing to do with you."
فاستفسرهم، فكان جوابهم، "ليس لك دخلٌ في هذا الأمر."
They called my name. They said, "We want her."
نادوا اسمي. وقالوا، "نريدها هي."
My bodyguard got out, said, "I can answer you.
فتقدم الحارس الشخصي، وقال، "يمكنني أن أجيبكم.
What do you want?"
ماذا الذي تريدونه؟"
They said, "Nothing." They called my name.
فأجابوا، "لا شيء." ونادوا اسمي.
And by that time, the women are yelling and screaming inside the car.
وبذلك الوقت، أخذ النساء يصرخن ويصحْن داخل السيارة.
I am very shaken up, and I told myself, this is it.
كنت مذعورةٌ حقاً, وأخبرت نفسي أن الوقت قد حان.
This time, we all are going to be killed.
سيتم قتلنا جميعا هذه المرة.
There is no doubt in my mind.
ليس هنالك أدنى شك.
But still, the moment comes, and you take strength
ولكن مع ذلك، حلت اللحظة، التي يجب أن تستجمع فيها قوتك
from whatever you believe and whatever you do.
من أي شيءٍ تؤمن به ومن أي شيءٍ تقوم به.
It's in your heart.
كل شيء محفور في داخلك.
You believe in your worth, and you can walk on it.
تُؤمن بقيمتك ويمكنك الاعتماد عليها.
So I just hold myself on the side of the car.
فتمالكت نفسي واقتربت من جانب السيارة.
My leg was shaking, and I got outside.
كانت رجلاي ترتعشان من الخوف، غادرت السيارة.
And I asked them, "What can I do for you?"
وسألتهم، "ما الذي يمكنني أن أفعله لكم؟"
You know what they said to me?
أتعرفون ما الذي قالوه لي؟
They said, "We know who you are.
قالوا، "نحن نعرف من أنتِ.
We know where you are going.
نعرف إلى أين أنت ذاهبةٌ.
Every day you go up north here and there.
تتجهين كل يوم إلى الشمالِ وتذهبين هنا وهناك.
You train women, you teach them
تقومين بتدريب النسوة وتعليمهن.
and also you give them an opportunity to have a job.
كما تمنحيهن فرصةً للحصول على وظيفةٍ.
You build their skills. How about us?"
تقومين بصقل مواهبهن. فماذا عنا؟"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
"And you know, how about us?
"وكما تعرفين، ماذا عنا نحن؟
What are we going to do?"
ما الذي سنقوم به؟"
I looked at them, and I said, "I don't know."
نظرت إليهم وقلت، "لا أعرف."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
They said, "It's OK.
أجابوني، " لا بأس،
The only thing we can do, what we know,
الشيء الوحيد الذي يمكننا القيام به، ونعرفه،
from the time we're born, we just hold the gun and kill.
منذ ولادتنا، هو الإمساك بالبندقية وإطلاق النار منها للقتل.
That's all we know."
هذا كل ما نعرفه."
And you know what that means.
وتعرفون ما الذي يعنيه هذا.
It's a trap to me, of course.
انها مصيدة للايقاع بي، بطبيعة الحال.
So I walk out of there. They said, "We'll let you go, go."
فابتعدت عنهم. فقالوا لي، "سوف نترككِ تذهبين، ارحلي."
And so I walked into the car, I sit in the car,
فاتجهت صوب السيارة وجلست في داخلها،
and I told the driver, "Turn around and go back to the office."
وقلت للسائق، "استدر ولنعد إلى المكتب."
At that time, we only were supporting girls.
في ذلك الوقت، كنا نقوم فقط بدعم الفتيات.
We only had money for women to train them,
كنا نملك المال الكافي لتدريب النساء فقط،
to send them to school, and nothing else.
لإرسالهن إلى المدرسة ولا شيء أكثر من ذلك.
By the time I came to the office,
وبوصولي إلى المكتب،
of course my trainers were gone.
اختفى جميع المدربون بالطبع.
They ran away home. Nobody stayed there.
هربوا بعيدا واحتموا بمنازلهم. لم يبقى أحدٌ هناك.
My bodyguard was the only one there,
حارسي الشخصي هو الوحيد الذي كان موجودا،
and my voice was completely gone.
فقدت صوتي تماماً.
I was shaken up, and I sat on my table,
كنت أرتعد جالسةً فوق طاولة المكتب،
and I said, "What am I going to do?"
سألت نفسي، "ماذا سأفعل؟"
How am I going to solve this problem?
كيف سأتمكن من حل هذه المشكلة؟
Because we had training going on up north already.
لأنه يوجد في الشمال تدريبات قد بدأت بالفعل.
Hundreds of women were there coming to get training.
يوجد مئات النساء هناك، قدمن من أجل التدريب.
So I was sitting there, all of a sudden, at this moment,
كنت جالسةً هناك أفكر وفجأة، في تلك اللحظة،
talking about momentum, we are,
نتحدث عن لحظة القوة الدافعة والعزيمة
at that moment,
في تلك اللحظة،
one of my wonderful donors called me about a report.
اتصلت واحدة من المتبرعات الرائعات من أجل الحصول على تقريرٍ.
And she asked me, "Sakena?" And I answered her.
وسألتني، "سكينة ؟" فأجبتها.
She said, "It's not you. What's wrong with you?"
قالت لي، "لست كالعادة، ما الذي أصابك؟"
I said, "Nothing." I tried to cover.
فأجبتها، "لا شيء." حاولت إخفاء ما حدث.
No matter what I tried to do, she didn't believe me,
مهما حاولت جاهدةً، لم تصدقني.
and she asked me again.
وسألتني مرة أخرى.
"OK, tell me what's going on?"
" حسنا، أخبريني ما الذي يحدث؟"
I told her the whole story.
فأخبرتها كامل القصة.
At that time, she said, "OK, you go next time, and you will help them.
وفي تلك اللحظة، قالت لي، "حسنا، عندما تذهبين مرة أخرى، ساعديهم.
You will help them."
قدمي لهم المساعدة."
And when, two days later, I went the same route,
بعد ذلك بيومين، عندما سلكت نفس الطريق،
and do you know, they were not in here,
لم يكونوا هناك،
they were a little back further,
فقد كانوا يقفون أبعد بقليل.
the same young men, standing up there and holding the rifle
نفس الشبان، واقفين ويحمل كل واحد منهم بندقية
and pointing to us to stop the car.
ويشيرون إلينا بالتوقف.
So we stopped the car.
أوقفنا السيارة.
I got out. I said, "OK, let's go with me."
نزلت من السيارة، وقلت، "حسنا، رافقوني."
And they said, "Yes."
فأجابوني، "حسناً"
I said, "On one condition, that whatever I say, you accept it."
فأضفت، "لكن لدي شرط واحد ، أن تقبلوا كل ما أقوله لكم."
And they said, yes, they do.
فأجابوا بالموافقة.
So I took them to the mosque,
اصطحبتهم إلى المسجد،
and to make a long story short,
ولألخص لكم القصة الطويلة،
I told them I'd give them teachers.
أخبرتهم أنني سأمنحهم معلمين.
Today, they are the best trainers.
فأصبحوا اليوم أفضل المدربين الموجودين.
They learn English,
تعلموا اللغة الانجليزية،
they learn how to be teachers,
تعلموا كيف يصبحوا معلمين،
they learn computers,
تعلموا استعمال الحاسوب،
and they are my guides.
وهم الآن يعتبرون مرشدون لنا.
Every area that is unknown to us in the mountain areas,
كل منطقة لا نعرفها في المناطق الجبلية،
they go with me. They are ahead, and we go.
يذهبون معنا إليها. يدلوننا على الطريق ونحن نتبعهم.
And they protect us.
ويقومون بحمايتنا.
And --
وهذا
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
That tells you that education transforms people.
وهذا يثبت لكم أن التنعليم يُغيّر الناس.
When you educate people,
عندما تفوم بتعليم الناس،
they are going to be different,
سيكونون مختلفين عما عليه،
and today all over,
والآن في كل مكانٍ،
we need to work for gender equality.
نحتاج إلى العمل من أجل تحقيق المساواة بين الجنسين.
We cannot only train women but forget about the men,
لا يمكننا تدريب النساء فقط وننسى الرجال،
because the men are the real people who are giving women the hardest time.
لأن الرجال هم السبب الرئيسي الذي يجعل النساء يمررن بأصعب الأوقات.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So we started training men because the men should know
لذلك بدأنا بتدريب الرجال لأنه يجب أن يعرفوا
the potential of women,
إمكانيات المرأة،
know how much these potential men has,
يعرفوا إلى أي مدى تصل إمكانيات الرجل،
and how much these women can do the same job they are doing.
وكيف يمكن لهؤلاء النساء القيام بنفس العمل الذي يقوم به الرجال.
So we are continuously giving training to men,
لذلك نستمر الآن بتدريب الرجالِ.
and I really believe strongly.
أملك إيمانا قويا.
I live in a country that was a beautiful country.
وأعيش في بلدٍ كان بلدا جميلا.
I just want to share this with you.
أريد فقط ان أشاركم هذا.
It was a beautiful country,
كان بلدا جميلا،
beautiful, peaceful country.
بلدا جميلا ومسالما.
We were going everywhere.
كنا نذهب إلى كل مكانٍ.
Women were getting education:
كانت النساء يحصلن على التعليم:
lawyer, engineer, teacher,
محاميات، مهندسات، معلمات،
and we were going from house to house.
وكنا ننتقل من منزلٍ إلى آخر.
We never locked our doors.
بدون أن نغلق أبوابنا أبدا.
But you know what happened to my country.
لكن هل تعرفون ما الذي حدث لبلدي؟
Today, people cannot walk out of their door without security issues.
اليوم، لا يستطيع الناس الخروج من منازلهم بدون أن يواجهوا مشكلاتٍ أمنية.
But we want the same Afghanistan we had before.
ولكننا نريد أن نسترجع أفغانستان التي كانت لدينا.
And I want to tell you the other side.
وأوّد أن أخبركم الجانب الآخر من القصة.
Today, the women of Afghanistan are working very, very hard.
اليوم، أصبحت النسوة في أفغانستان يعملن بجدٍّ.
They are earning degrees. They are training to be lawyers.
يحصلن على الدرجات العلمية والشهادات , يتدربن ليصبحن محامياتٍ.
They are training to be doctors, back again.
ومرة أخرى ,يتدربن ليصبحن طبيباتٍ،
They are training to be teachers,
يتدربن ليكنّ معلماتٍ،
and they are running businesses.
ويقمن بإدارة مشاريع تجارية.
So it is so wonderful
هذا أمرا رائعا للغاية
to see people like that reach their complete potential,
أن ترى أشخاصا من هذا القبيل يصلون لأقصى إمكانياتهم،
and all of this is going to happen.
كل ذلك سيتحقق.
I want to share this with you,
أريد مشاركة هذا معكم،
because of love,
بسبب الحب،
because of compassion,
بسبب الرحمة،
and because of trust and honesty.
وبسبب الثقة والصدق.
If you have these few things with you,
اذا كنت تملك هذه الأشياء القليلة والبسيطة،
you will accomplish.
ستحقق ذلك.
We have one poet, Mawl훮n훮 R큰m카.
لدينا شاعر يدعى جَلَال الدِّين الرُّومي.
He said that by having compassion
قال أنه إذا كنت تملك الرحمة
and having love, you can conquer the world.
والحب يمكنك غزو العالم بسهولةٍ.
And I tell you, we could.
وأنا أخبركم أنه يمكننا ذلك.
And if we could do it in Afghanistan,
ويمكننا تحقيق ذلك في أفغانستان.
I am sure 100 percent that everyone can do it in any part of the world.
أنا متأكدة تماما أنه يمكن لأي شخص من أي مكان من العالم القيام بذلك.
Thank you very, very much.
شكرا جزيلا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you. Thank you.
شكرا لكم. شكرا.